GLORY
DAYS!
By the decision of Ying Zheng, the king that wished to unite all of China,
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
天下統一の道を行く王 嬴政(えいせい)のもと
秦国(しんこく)は 隣国 魏(ぎ)への侵攻を開始した
the State of Qin began its invasion of the neighboring State of Wei.
Wang Ben, Meng Tian, and Xin.
王賁(おうほん) 蒙恬(もうてん) そして信(しん)
未来の大将軍たらんとする兵(つわもの)が―
Three soldiers wishing to become Great Generals are gathered here
今ここに集い
新しき時代を迎えようとしていた
trying to usher in a new age.
So...
（羌瘣(きょうかい)）だから…
So when this war is over, I'm leaving here.
（羌瘣）だから この戦が
終わったら 私は ここを出ていく
I don't know how many months or years it'll take...
何か月…
何年かかるか分からないけど…
but I'll make sure I get my revenge.
きっちり敵(かたき)を討つ
And when that's done, if I come back again...
（羌瘣）そして それが終わって
また帰ってきたら…
When that happens, I think I'll really be able to move forward with all of you.
そのときは 私も ちゃんと
お前たちと一緒に前に進めると思う
Let's win, Qiang Lei!
（信）勝とうぜ 羌瘣
Right.
Qin
Wei
Han
Zhao
Xiangyang
Anyi
Luoyang
Handan
Daliang
Shanyang, the cornerstone to Western Wei's defense, is home to four castles.
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）魏国の
西を押さえる重要拠点 山陽(さんよう)には
Shanyang
４つの城があり
To the West of them is the Liuyin Plain.
それらの西に
流尹(るい)平野が広がっている
Liuyin Plain
だが 平野といっても そこは―
Although it's called a plain,
it was a complex area that also contains mountains, forests, and wetland regions.
山や森 湿地帯などが入り組んだ
複雑な地形を擁していた
While its terrain makes maneuvering troops difficult,
軍を動かすのが困難な代わりに―
さまざまな作戦を展開させることが
できる この流尹平野が―
it allows for a large variety of tactics to be possible.
This is the land which the man matchless in the art of war, General Lian Po, chose for the decisive battle.
無類の戦上手 廉頗(れんぱ)将軍が
選んだ決戦の地であった
（廉頗）来おったな 蒙驁(もうごう)
So you've come, have you, Meng Ao?!
I still do not quite understand.
（姜燕(きょうえん)）
それにしても 少々 解(げ)せませんな
I did not think Meng Ao was someone strong enough to make you this happy, my lord.
（姜燕）蒙驁に殿を喜ばせるほどの
力量があるとは思えませんが…
（廉頗）いかにも
Indeed!
Meng Ao is an exceedingly average general...
蒙驁は至極凡庸な将軍じゃ
But despite that, he has quite
a military record, don't you think?
だが…
そのわりには なかなかの戦歴を
残しているとは思わんか？
Wang Qi told me this:
王騎(おうき)が言っておった
“蒙驁は才能の代わりに
強力な２本の剣(つるぎ)を持っている”とな
"In lieu of talent, Meng Ao possesses two mighty swords."
Two swords?
（輪虎(りんこ)）２本の剣？
It seems the two Vice Generals Meng Ao carries with him
（廉頗）
蒙驁の抱えている２人の副将が―
いまだ 世に知られていない
バケモノだそうだ
are monsters that are still unknown to the world.
さ～て 蒙驁よ
So then, Meng Ao, show me how you wield them...
存分に
振るってみせてもらおうかのぅ
２本の剣とやらを！
Those two swords of yours.
Clash!
The State of Qin Army Supreme Commander, General Meng Ao, arrived at the location of the decisive battle, the Liuyin Plain.
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）決戦の地 流尹平野に―
秦国軍の総大将 蒙驁将軍が
到着した
フォ？
ほう…
We have awaited your arrival.
（桓騎(かんき)）お待ちしておりました
（王翦(おうせん)）蒙驁大将軍
General Meng Ao.
（蒙驁）
フォフォフォ… ２人とも ご苦労
Good work, you two.
Who are those two?
何だ？ あの２人は
（蒙恬）
そっか お前は まだ知らないよな
Oh.
You still don't know, huh?
ハァ… また出た
And there you are again.
あれが じいさまの２人の副将…
（信）副将？
Those are Grandfather's two Vice Generals.
Vice Generals?
General Huan Ji and General Wang Jian.
（蒙恬）桓騎将軍と王翦将軍だ
Huan Ji and Wang Jian? Never heard of 'em.
桓騎と王翦？ 知らねえな
…てことは 大したことねえな
So they're probably not much.
何言ってんだ 信
２人とも バケモノだぞ
What're you talking about, Xin?
Those two are monsters.
えっ？ バケモノ？
Monsters?!
Speaking honestly, most of Grandfather's achievements are thanks to them.
（蒙恬）実際のところ―
じいさまの功績のほとんどは
あの２人の手によるもの
Those two haven't become more
preeminent as generals because...
２人の名が武将として
広まっていないのは―
２人とも訳ありだからだ
（信）訳あり？
both of them have a certain "reason".
Reason?
Huan Ji was originally the head of a huge band of thieves whose territory was the Southern mountains of the State of Qin.
桓騎将軍は もともと―
秦国の南の山々を
縄張りにしていた大盗賊団の首領だ
What?!
なに？
（蒙恬）性格は残忍
He has a very cruel personality.
武将として召し抱えられてからも
盗賊時代の気性の荒さが抜けない
Even now that he's been employed as a general,
his rough temper from his days as a thief still remains.
I've heard that one time when he captured a castle,
かつて ある城を攻め落としたとき
桓騎は自ら 住人全員の
首をはねたといわれている
Huan Ji personally cut off the heads of every one of the inhabitants.
The heads of... every one of the inhabitants?
住人全員の首を…
（蒙恬）“首斬り桓騎”
Huan Ji the Beheader.
That's a nickname that still follows him around, even now.
それが
今でも ついて回る彼の異名だ
最低の野郎じゃねえか！
So he's a piece of this then, ain't he?
なんで
そんなヤツを副将なんかに…
Why would somebody like that be a Vice General?
戦の天才だからだ
（信）ハッ…
Because he's a genius when it comes to war.
（蒙恬）彼が盗賊だったころ
その暴虐を止めるため―
When he was a thief, the State of Qin sent punitive forces to stop his tyranny countless times.
秦国は幾度となく討伐軍を送った
But without having anyone to teach him, Huan Ji was able to defeat the punitive forces
だが 誰から教わったわけでもない
桓騎独自の兵法の前に―
討伐軍は
ただの一度も勝てなかった
with his private soldiers every single time.
For Grandfather, taking Huan Ji under him is certainly not an honorable thing,
確かに じいさまにとって
桓騎を抱えるのは不名誉なことだが
それを差し引いても
彼の力は余りある代物なんだ
but his power simply outweighs that.
Then what about the other general, Wang Jian?
んじゃ
もう１人の王翦って将軍は？
General Wang Jian is Wang Ben's father.
王翦将軍は王賁の父親だ
（蒙恬）つまり―
In other words, he is the current head of the famous Wang Family, the one that General Wang Qi comes from.
あの王騎将軍を輩出した名門
王(おう)一族の現在の頭首だ
The head of... General Wang Qi's family?
王騎将軍の一族の頭首…
Young Master!
（じい）若 お早く！
Hurry up!
（蒙恬）ほ～い 今行く！
Okay, coming!
Hold up, Meng Tian!
待て 蒙恬！
（蒙恬）ウワッ…
You said both generals had specific reasons for not being famous.
（信）副将が
２人とも訳ありって言ったよな？
王翦将軍には
どんな訳があるんだ？
What sorta reason does General Wang Jian have?
General Wang Jian is the "most dangerous person" in the State of Qin.
王翦将軍は秦国一の危険人物だ
That's why he's been chased to positions in the shadows since the age of King Zhao.
だから 昭王(しょうおう)の時代から ずっと
日陰の地位に追いやられている
Why's that?
それ どういうことだよ？
From what I've heard, that man's got a certain ambition.
聞いた話じゃ なんでも
あの人には野望があってね
He supposedly wants to become king.
自分が
“王さま”になりたいんだってさ
He wants... to be king?!
自分が王さまに？
こたびも頼りにしておるぞい
２人とも
I hope I can count on you two again for this!
Meanwhile, all units of the State of Wei Army arrived at the Liuyin Plain.
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）一方 魏国軍も
全軍が流尹平野に到着し
本陣を張る馬練山(ばれんさん)の頂に…
They set up their headquarters, and at the top of Malian Mountain...
Supreme Commander Bai Guixi stands!
総大将 白亀西(はくきさい)が立った
うん？
（玄峰(げんぽう)）うん？
（介子坊(かいしぼう)）な… なんですと！
What?!
The lord is not Supreme Commander?!
（輪虎）殿が総大将ではない？
（介子坊）白亀西なんて知らんぞ
誰だ？ それは
I don't know any Bai Guixi!
Who the hell is that?!
He was one of the men serving as Vice General to General Wu Qing
（姜燕）
確か 先の秦国と魏国の戦で―
呉慶(ごけい)将軍の
副将を務めた ひとりでは？
in the previous war between the State of Qin and the State of Wei, if I'm not mistaken.
（玄峰）ああ 王騎の ひとにらみで
退散したとかいう ふぬけじゃな
Yes! Isn't he that coward they say retreated after getting a single glare from Wang Qi?
I can't hear that!
（白亀西）聞こえない…
聞こえていないぞ ひと言も
I can't hear one word of it...
So, surprised, are ya?
どうだ？ 驚いたじゃろう
黙っとった甲斐(かい)があったわ
ヌハハハハッ！
Looks like it was worth staying quiet on it!
This is no laughing matter, my lord!
笑い事ではありませんぞ 殿！
これは 一体 どういうことですか？
What in the world is going on here?
なぜ あのような者が総大将に？
Why is such a person Supreme Commander?
うむ… 第一の理由は士気じゃ
（介子坊）はぁ？
Well, the biggest reason is morale.
Other states are a given, but even within the State of Wei,
他国は無論 魏国の国内でも―
わしは
この３年 王の信頼を得られず―
in three years I have not gained the king's trust and stood on a battlefield.
戦場に
立てなかったことになっておる
それが いきなり大将になっても
魏国の兵士たちの士気は上がらん
So if I'm a Great General all of a sudden, that definitely won't boost the State of Wei soldiers' morale.
Indeed.
確かに
But more importantly,
（廉頗）それよりは
何の取り柄もないが―
by making this guy who's got no real worth to him but is for some reason liked by the people, Chin Genxi the commander...
なぜか国民に好かれておる
チンゲンサイを大将にして…
（輪虎）殿 白亀西です
My lord, it's Bai Guixi.
It's easier to control things from the background that way.
（廉頗）それを裏から
わしが操るほうが戦いやすいわい
Though, I won't say there aren't any other reasons.
まあ ほかにも
理由がないこともないがのぅ
Oh. You mean you feel guilty because of some lingering affection for the State of Zhao.
ああっ！ 趙国(ちょうこく)に未練があるから
後ろめたいと…
（殴る音）
あいて…
Ow.
Understood, sir.
分かりました
殿の決定ならば 我らは喜んで
If that is your decision, we will gladly oblige, my lord.
やっぱり うれしそうですね
戦場にいるのが
You really are happy to be back on the battlefield, aren't you?
（廉頗）うぬらもな
So are you guys.
白亀西ーっ！
Bai Guixi!
Come over here!
こっちへ来い いつものをやる！
We're gonna do our usual thing!
うわぁ！
うん？ いつもの？
Usual thing?
Jie Zifang!
介子坊！
My lord!
殿！
（廉頗）ンンッ！ 武運を祈る！
I pray for your good fortune in battle!
（介子坊）殿も ご武運を！
As do I, my lord!
うむ…
Next, Lun Hu!
次 輪虎！
Allrighty! Man, I missed this!
（輪虎）はいは～い！ 久々だ！
武運を祈る！
（輪虎）効く～！
I pray for your good fortune in battle!
It's working!
次 姜燕！
（姜燕）はっ…
Next, Jiang Yan!
Yes, sir.
Next, old man Xuan Feng!
次 玄峰じじい！
You really think I'd do that?
（玄峰）やるかい そんなもん
（廉頗）ハハハハッ！
Next, Bai Guixi!
次 白亀西！
N-No. I don't think I...
い… いえ！ 私は そんな…
I pray for your good fortune in battle!
（廉頗）武運を祈るぞ！
It... It hurts...
い… 痛い！
い… いや… あ… 熱い！
N-No, it's hot?!
Wh-What is this feeling...?
な… 何だ？ この感じ
この…
This... uplifting sensation?!
高揚感！
Power is...
腹の底から力が…
welling from... the pit of my stomach!
力が湧き上がって…
Here I come!
くるー！
それでは そろそろ始めようかのぅ
Now then, it's about time we got started.
Sir!
フッ… 配置に就け！
Take your places!
Lian Po
（伝令）敵 魏国軍の総大将は
廉頗にあらず！ 白亀西なり！
The enemy Supreme Commander is not Lian Po, it is Bai Guixi!
I repeat! The enemy Supreme Commander is Bai Guixi!
繰り返す
敵の総大将は白亀西なり！
Lian Po's not the Supreme Commander?! What's going on?!
廉頗が総大将じゃない？
どういうことだ？
Lord Meng Tian, they are saying it is not Lian Po.
（じい）
蒙恬さま 廉頗ではないと…
Ah, now this is bothersome...
やっかいなことに なったな…
これで 廉頗が
本陣にいるとは限らなくなった
That means that Lian Po won't be limited to the headquarters.
Lian Po...
（蒙驁）廉頗…
貴様が どう動こうと
もはや惑うことはない
No matter what moves you make, I will no longer waver.
I have made my resolve!
わしは もう腹をくくったぞい
Lord Wang Jian, there is a signal fire from the headquarters.
（副官）
王翦さま 本陣より のろしが…
It says "I wish you good fortune in battle."
“武運を祈る”とのことです
（桓騎）フッ… 珍しいな
Oh, that's unusual.
あの白老が高ぶっておられる
The White Elder is getting excited.
廉頗よ
最後に笑うのは このわしじゃ
Lian Po, the one to have the last laugh will be me!
First formation of the vanguard unit, forward!
先鋒隊(せんぽうたい)第１陣 前へ！
So the time has finally come.
（楚水(そすい)）いよいよですね
（信）ハッ… ああ
The Yufeng Unit is coming through!
（兵士）玉鳳(ぎょくほう)隊が通るぞ！
Wang Ben... Those guys were absorbed into the first formation?
（信）王賁… あいつら
第１陣に組み込まれたのか
クッ…
また先に手柄を上げられちまう
He's gonna render achievements before me again...
急造の千人隊で第１陣とは…
厳しいな
Sending a newly-formed Thousand-Man Unit into a first formation... that sure is harsh...
正直 王賁も
そのクジは引きたくなかったはずだ
Wang Ben probably honestly wishes he didn't draw that lot...
Lord Ben, being in the first formation is truly an unexpected opportunity, isn't it?
（番陽(ばんよう)）賁さま 第１陣とは
願ってもない機会を得ましたな
Now we will show not only the enemy State of Wei Army, but also our allies, just how powerful the Yufeng Unit is!
敵の魏国軍は もとより―
味方にも玉鳳隊の力を
知らしめてやりましょう
Yeah.
あの人にもな…
And him, as well.
This is a message from General Tu Men to all soldiers of the first formation!
（土門(どもん)）将軍 土門より
第１陣の全兵士に伝える！
State of Qin General
Tu Men
こたびの戦の流れを
決する重要な初戦である
This is a critical battle that will determine the flow of this war!
Trample the enemy with all of your strength!
全力で
敵をたたきつぶせー！
Lord Lun Hu, preparations for sortie are complete.
（副官）
輪虎さま 出撃の準備 整いました
はいは～い
Okay!
Quiet, isn't it?
静かだな…
Is this really a good idea for this to be our army's first formation?
我が軍の第１陣は
本当に これで大丈夫なのか？
First formation...
第１陣…
突撃だー！
（兵士たち）オーッ！
charge!
How 'bout we get going?
いこうか
Do not falter! Surround that young lance user!
（武将Ａ）ひるむな！
その若い槍使(やりつか)いを
取り囲んで しとめろ！
This is bad. The first formation is being pushed back.
マズイ
第１陣が勢いで押されている
第２陣を動かすか？
Should we send in the second formation?!
ヌハハハハッ！ 慌てるな
Don't piss yourself!
うぬら魏国の兵士の
力が発揮されるのは―
We're just starting to bring out the power of you State of Wei soldiers!
ここからじゃ
（白亀西）えっ？
うん 第５隊は左に押し込もう
（部下Ａ）はっ！
Let's push the fifth unit to the left.
Yes, sir!
And how about we shift the seventh unit right and have the eighth unit charge?
第７隊を右にずらして
第８隊を突入させようか
Yes, sir!
Fifth unit! Get in formation!
（武将Ｃ）第５隊 陣形を整えよ
左に進んで 敵をたたくぞ！
Let's march left and crush the enemy!
Eighth unit! Charge!
（武将Ｄ）第８隊 突撃だー！
（輪虎）へえ…
The State of Wei soldiers are as overly-serious as the lord said.
魏国の兵士は生真面目だって
殿が言ってたとおりだ
Even with an outsider like me directing them, they follow orders to a T.
よそ者の僕が指揮官でも
命令どおり きっちり戦っている
偉いなぁ
Impressive.
Okey doke.
よしよし　それじゃ…
Guess it's time I got started, too.
そろそろ 僕も始めようか
Our army is pushing back!
我が軍が押し戻した！
しかも 攻勢に転じている
And now they're on the attack!
ウワッ！
（廉頗）フフッ…
So you finally got going, eh, Lun Hu?
動きだしたな… 輪虎
General Tu Men!
（伝令）土門将軍！
太雲(たいうん)千人将が討ち死にされました！
Thousand-Man General Tai Yun was killed!
（土門）な… なに？
Wh-What?!
クッ…
太雲隊は今回 急造した千人将
The Tai Yun Unit was one of the Thousand-Man Units we'd just constructed.
やはり力不足だったか
I knew they weren't strong enough.
General! This time the Ting Bi Unit was attacked by an elite enemy unit!
（伝令２）将軍！ 今度は延比(えんぴ)隊が
敵の精鋭部隊に襲撃され
延比千人将が討ち死にされました！
（土門）なんだと！
Thousand-Man General Ting Bi has been killed!
What?!
延比隊も太雲隊と同じく
臨時編成でできた急造の千人隊だが
The Ting Bi Unit was another sudden and specially organized unit like the Tai Yun Unit.
ハッ… まさか…
Could it be... they're being... targeted?!
狙われているのか？
The fourth unit is fighting a hard battle!
（玉隊員１）第４隊が苦戦中です！
（番陽）第２隊を呼び戻して―
Call back the second unit and have them reinforce the fourth unit!
第４隊の救援に向かわせろ
（玉隊員１）はっ！
Yes, sir!
The right defensive unit is being pushed back as well!
（玉隊員２）
右の守備隊も押されています！
What are you doing?!
何をしている！
第７隊 動きが遅いぞ！
You're slow, seventh unit!
The ninth unit was caught by the enemy from the rear!
（玉隊員３）
第９隊 後方で敵に捕まりました！
（番陽）なにぃ？
What?!
The newly-added 700 men have slower senses than the Yufeng Unit's original 300.
新しく加入した700人の隊の動きが
常に
元の玉鳳隊の感覚より遅れている
Zhou! Go aid the ninth unit!
（番陽）舟(しゅう) 第９隊を助けに行け！
賁さまは わしがお守りする
I will protect Lord Ben!
（王賁）動きが遅れた分の
ほころびを繕うのに 力を割かれる
To mend the open seam of their slower movements
our strength is being split apart.
These newly-added soldiers are quite elite,
今回 加入した兵士たちも
精鋭ではあったが
生え抜きの玉鳳隊300人と
力の差があることは分かっていた
but there's a clear difference between them and the native-born Yufeng Unit.
But I never expected that difference in strength to be this much of a constraint in fighting together.
…が その力の差が 共に戦ううえで
これほど大きな枷(かせ)になるとは
（玉隊員４）
王賁さま！ 番陽副長！
Lord Wang Ben!
Vice Captain Pan Yang!
New enemies are approaching from the left!
左からも新手が来ます！
（番陽）左もか！
The left, too?!
ええい 新手には第３隊を充てろ！
Assign third unit to the unit on the left!
But more importantly, the right! Hurry and reorganize the right formation!
それより 右の…
右の陣形の立て直しを急がせよ！
No... This comes first.
（王賁）いや…
こっちが先だ
What?!
If you watch closely, it doesn't take long to spot the difference
（輪虎）統率された隊と
そうでない隊は―
between a unit that has leadership, and one that doesn't.
注意して見れば すぐ分かる
Of course, the former is strong and the latter is weak.
もちろん 前者は強くて 後者は弱い
And the reason this State of Qin Army has several weak units
そして この秦国軍に
いくつか弱い隊があるのは―
is because of what I did; assassinating noteworthy Thousand-Man Generals, forcing temporary ones to be formed.
目についた千人将を暗殺して
臨時の千人隊を作らせた僕の功績
そうか…
I see.
So you were the one going around slaying our Thousand-Man Generals at the Jinli Barrier.
近利関(きんりかん)で こちらの千人将を
斬って回ったのは お前か
So then, I'm going to be taking your life, temporary Thousand-Man General.
…ということで
命をもらうよ 臨時の千人将君
Protect Lord Ben!
（番陽）賁さまを守れ！
ハハッ… 守れるかな？
Do you think you can?
Get out of the way.
どけ
ハッ… 賁さま…
Lord... Ben...
I'll do it.
俺がやる
Preview
Xuan Feng's Scheme
End